Guide to the James S. Trefil papers, 1965-2009
George Mason University Libraries
- James Trefil papers
  - GMU Law and Economics Center: Notes- Materials- Faculty- Participants- General- Miscellaneous- (Folder 1-6, Box 95)
  - Extinction: Proposal for Book "Nemesis"- Miscellaneous- Interviews- Time Scale Paleo.- Papers 1983- 84- Modeling- Articles (Folder 7-14, Box 95)
  - Sun, undated (Folder 1, Box 96)
  - Clouds, undated (Folder 2, Box 96)
  - Astronomy I, 1992 (Folder 3-4, Box 96)
  - CFA-I, Smithsonian, Fermllab, MMT/LMSC, APS Washington, miscellaneous (Folder 5, Box 96)
  - Beach articles (1 of 3), 1983 (Folder 1, Box 97)
  - Beach articles (2 of 3), 1983 (Folder 2, Box 97)
  - Beach articles (3 of 3), 1983 (Folder 3, Box 97)
    Includes contact sheets, photographs, and negatives
  - Mountains (1 of 3) (Folder 4, Box 97)
  - Mountains (2 of 3) (Folder 5, Box 97)
  - Mountains (3 of 3) (Folder 6, Box 97)
  - Mind of God papers (1 of 2), 1980 (Folder 1, Box 98)
  - Mind of God papers (2 of 2), 1980 (Folder 2, Box 98)
  - Physics 101 and 102 exams, 1984-1985 (Folder 3, Box 98)
  - Physics 101 exam notes, 1978-1982 (Folder 4, Box 98)
  - Physics 103 quizzes and exams, 1980-1982 (Folder 5, Box 98)
  - Astronomy 105 (Folder 1-2, Box 99)
  - Astronomy 105 and 106 exams, 1991-1992 (Folder 3, Box 99)
  - Miscellaneous physics notes (Folder 4, Box 99)
  - Physics 2S (Folder 1-3, Box 100)
  - Physics 181 (Folder 4-5, Box 100)
  - WGBH, 2001 (Folder 1, Box 101)
  - NPR scripts, 1986-1987 (Folder 2, Box 101)
  - Stenotic flow - dressing time (Folder 3, Box 101)
  - Naturalist project (Folder 4, Box 101)
  - Physics 104E, 1979 (Folder 5-6, Box 101)
  - Liberal arts project, 1997 (Folder 1, Box 102)
  - Opening doors to the future and notes on a liberal arts physics text, 2001 (Folder 2, Box 102)
  - E-mail reply on "Politics and Prose" from Kate Pruss to James Trefil, January 30, 2004 (Folder 3, Box 102)
  - E-mail on "follow up from your visit" from Robin Dennis to James Trefil, December 1, 2003 (Folder 4, Box 102)
  - E-mail on "States help threatened bird at expense of fisherman" from Robin Dennis to James Trefil, April 9, 2004 (Folder 5, Box 102)
  - Human nature (Folder 6, Box 102)
  - Facsimile transmission cover sheet, 2003 (Folder 7, Box 102)
  - The second step (Folder 8-9, Box 102)
  - Science and religion, 2000 (Folder 10, Box 102)
  - Carnegie, 2000-2001 (Folder 11, Box 102)
  - Globalization and education conference, 2001-2002 (Folder 12, Box 102)
  - Miscellaneous articles (Folder 13, Box 102)
  - USA weekend articles, 1998-1999 (Folder 14, Box 102)
  - Chi-Tampa 2002, 2001-2002 (Folder 15, Box 102)
  - Brookings, Judicial education program, 2004 (Folder 16, Box 102)
  - Pop science quiz, 2003 (Folder 17, Box 102)
  - Big ideas, 2004 (Folder 18, Box 102)
  - Weather, 2000 (Folder 19, Box 102)
  - Macedonia, 2000 (Folder 20, Box 102)
  - Macedonia translation (Folder 21, Box 102)
  - Cyril and Methodius University, 1997 (Folder 22, Box 102)
  - Second step - first revision (Folder 1, Box 103)
  - Second step - working revision, 2003 (Folder 2, Box 103)
  - Adler planetarium, 1997-1999 (Folder 3, Box 103)
  - H-M proposal XX 452 A3, 1998 (Folder 4, Box 103)
  - Macedonia back file, 1999-2000 (Folder 5, Box 103)
  - Macedonia back file, 1998 (Folder 6, Box 103)
  - Second step proposals, 2002 (Folder 7, Box 103)
  - Second step revision notes, 2002-2003 (Folder 8, Box 103)
  - Second step revisions (Folder 9, Box 103)
  - Climate information, 2002 (Folder 10, Box 103)
  - Henry Holt and company author questionnaires (Folder 11, Box 103)
  - Index for human nature (Folder 12, Box 103)
  - Syndicate column (Folder 13, Box 103)
  - Unknown correspondence, 1994-1995 (Folder 14, Box 103)
  - Next 5 XX 452 H9 (Folder 15, Box 103)
  - Chronicle, 1994-1995 (Folder 16, Box 103)
  - Future H-M items (Folder 17, Box 103)
  - Nature promotion file, 2003 (Folder 1, Box 104)
  - God and science (Folder 2, Box 104)
  - Underground, 1985 (Folder 3, Box 104)
  - Mars, fossils, 1995 (Folder 4, Box 104)
  - Completed files, March 25 and 30, 1995 (Folder 5, Box 104)
  - The edge of the unknown, ready for final revision, June 1995 (Folder 6, Box 104)
  - Symmetry proposal, 2000 (Folder 7, Box 104)
  - 500 year proposal, 2004 (Folder 8, Box 104)
  - Evolution (Folder 9, Box 104)
  - Geo-engineering, 1996 (Folder 10, Box 104)
  - MacAyeal, 1993 (Folder 11, Box 104)
  - MacAyeal II, 1993-1995 (Folder 12, Box 104)
  - Untitled, 1996-2001 (Folder 1, Box 105)
  - Untitled, 1996 (Folder 2, Box 105)
  - Consciousness file, 1995-1996 (Folder 3, Box 105)
  - "Between Darwin and the supercomputer" (Folder 4, Box 105)
  - "Are we unique?" (Folder 5, Box 105)
  - C.A.S. and Nature museum, 1996-1997 (Folder 6, Box 105)
  - Columbia College, 1996-1997 (Folder 7, Box 105)
  - Amsterdam, 1995-1997 (Folder 8, Box 105)
  - EM9T back file, astronomy text 2?, 1997-1999 (Folder 9, Box 105)
  - Everyday science, 1997-2001 (Folder 1, Box 106)
  - July meeting, 2003 (Folder 2, Box 106)
  - Holt meeting, 2003 (Folder 3, Box 106)
  - Reading notes (non-Physics) (Folder 4, Box 106)
  - Robinson report, 2001 (Folder 5, Box 106)
  - Orals (Folder 6, Box 106)
  - APS chapter 8 (Folder 7, Box 106)
  - Marshall committee, 1995-1997 (Folder 8, Box 106)
  - Dilenschneider, 1999 (Folder 9, Box 106)
  - Report, 2003-2004 (Folder 10, Box 106)
  - Untitled, 2002-2003 (Folder 11, Box 106)
  - Macedonia, Science news, 2004 (Folder 12, Box 106)
  - AAAS (Copust and Fellow), 1997-2003 (Folder 13, Box 106)
  - Richard London, June 2004 (Folder 14, Box 106)
  - McD - L Ohio, 2003 (Folder 15, Box 106)
  - Robinson report, 2000 (Folder 16, Box 106)
  - First draft working title: The Second Step (Folder 17-19, Box 106)
  - Smithsonian, 2001-2002 (Folder 20, Box 106)
  - Quarterly report, 2002 (Folder 21, Box 106)
  - Frontiers, 2002-2004 (Folder 22, Box 106)
  - McDougal-Littel backfile, 2002 (Folder 1, Box 107)
  - Bell's theorem (Folder 2, Box 107)
  - Index specs for Trefil, human nature, 2004 (Folder 3, Box 107)
  - Human nature master set - first pass pages, December 18, 2003 (Folder 4-5, Box 107)
  - Human nature master set - second pass pages, January 26, 2004 (Folder 6-7, Box 107)
  - Human nature master set - third pass pages, February 18, 2004 (Folder 8-9, Box 107)
  - The international center for the advancement of scientific literacy - science and democracy, 1993 (Folder 10, Box 107)
  - Phi Beta Kappa Society, 2003 (Folder 11, Box 107)
  - Human nature duplicate set - first pass pages, December 18, 2003 (Folder 1-2, Box 108)
  - Human nature duplicate set - second pass pages, January 26, 2004 (Folder 3-4, Box 108)
  - Human nature master (Folder 5-6, Box 108)
  - Developing a science program: from concept to classroom, keynote speaker, 2003 (Folder 7, Box 108)
  - Robinson professor effort reports; course descriptions and student ratings, 2001-2002 (Folder 8, Box 108)
  - Sabbatical expenses; Marshall?, 2002-2004 (Folder 9, Box 108)
  - The sciences: an integrated approach fourth edition cover page and biography (Folder 10, Box 108)
  - "Why science?", draft and editing (Folder 1, Box 109)
  - "Grand questions", 2006 (Folder 2, Box 109)
  - Grand research questions in the solid earth sciences briefing book, July 19-20, 2006 (Folder 3, Box 109)
  - Solid earth sciences, 2006 (Folder 4, Box 109)
  - "1 S V", 2006 (Folder 5, Box 109)
  - Final College of Science report, 2004 (Folder 6, Box 109)
  - College of Science report, 2004 (Folder 1, Box 110)
  - College of Science committee, 2004 (Folder 2, Box 110)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 2004-2005 (Folder 3, Box 110)
  - Magazine story ideas, 2004 (Folder 4, Box 110)
  - Communications, 1978-1983 (Folder 5, Box 110)
  - Gemant award, 2000-2002 (Folder 6, Box 110)
  - Miscellaneous old papers and calculations (Folder 7, Box 110)
  - "EDC" and magazine articles, 2006 (Folder 8, Box 110)
  - Smithsonian magazine - quarterly reports - James Trefil, volume I, 1987-1990 (Folder 9, Box 110)
  - Smithsonian magazine - quarterly reports - James Trefil, volume II, 1991-1996 (Folder 10, Box 110)
  - Smithsonian magazine - quarterly reports - James Trefil, volume III, 1997-2001 (Folder 11, Box 110)
  - Floppy disks (Box 111)
  - Floppy disks (Box 112)
  - College of Science - organization and reports, 2005 (Folder 1, Box 113)
  - Papers from "Why science?", I, 2007 (Folder 2, Box 113)
  - Papers from "Why science?", II, 2005 (Folder 3, Box 113)
  - Papers from "Why science?", III, 2005 (Folder 4, Box 113)
  - Papers from "Why science?", IV, 2006 (Folder 5, Box 113)
  - Physics syllaby and exams, 1978-1979 (Folder 6, Box 113)
  - A course in general science/scientific literacy by Robert M. Hazen and James Trefil (Folder 1, Box 114)
  - Brittanica, 2005 (Folder 2, Box 114)
  - Educational leadership, 2009 (Folder 3, Box 114)
  - Gemant committee, 2003-2008 (Folder 4, Box 114)
  - Hominid trap, 1994-1995 (Folder 5, Box 114)
  - Intelligent design, 2005-2006 (Folder 6, Box 114)
  - Judicial education retreat, September 21-23, 2005 (Folder 7, Box 114)
  - Liberal education, 2007 (Folder 8, Box 114)
  - Metabolism first proposal, 2007 (Folder 9, Box 114)
  - Mining, undated (Folder 10, Box 114)
  - Morowitz project, 2005-2006 (Folder 11, Box 114)
  - Neutrino astronomy article, 2009 (Folder 12, Box 114)
  - New horizon, 2009 (Folder 13, Box 114)
  - New planet, 1991-1992 (Folder 1, Box 115)
  - Oersted, 2005 (Folder 2, Box 115)
  - Origin of life, American Science, 2007-2009 (Folder 3, Box 115)
  - Origin of life, astronomy, 2008 (Folder 4, Box 115)
  - Phi Beta Kappa book award, 2007-2009 (Folder 5, Box 115)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 2007 (Folder 6, Box 115)
  - Physical science McD - L, 2004-2006 (Folder 7, Box 115)
  - Physics and solids, Dover, 2009 (Folder 8, Box 115)
  - Post office, 2009 (Folder 9, Box 115)
  - Reviews; 10 ideas; Istanbul, undated (Folder 10, Box 115)
  - Santa Fe Journal, 2005 (Folder 11, Box 115)
  - Science academy, 2005-2006 (Folder 12, Box 115)
  - Science and the law, 2004-2006 (Folder 13, Box 115)
  - Science and the law II, 2004-2005 (Folder 14, Box 115)
  - Science evaluation group, 2005 (Folder 15, Box 115)
  - Science matters, circa 2007 (Folder 16, Box 115)
  - Science matters: achieving scientific literacy, revisions, 1991 (Folder 17, Box 115)
  - The Sciences, sixth edition, 2008 (Folder 18, Box 115)
  - The Sciences: an integrated approach, fifth edition, 2005 (Folder 19, Box 115)
  - SFI bulletin, aging, 2006 (Folder 20, Box 115)
  - SFI periodic table (Folder 1, Box 116)
  - Trefil chapter 17, 2006 (Folder 2, Box 116)
  - Uncertainty proposal, 2008 (Folder 3, Box 116)
  - Washington Post book world, 2008 (Folder 4, Box 116)
  - Wonder stories, 2007 (Folder 5, Box 116)